In just a couple of seconds
Spain is about to get its first
total solar eclipse in over 100 years.
And we're here with NASA
to film it from space.
But we almost didn't do this video
because it turns out
there are a great couple videos
on solar eclipses on YouTube,
and we just thought
we couldn't add anything.
But then we started looking.
[laughs]
Oh my God, that's insane!
And it turns out...
Oh, I can't, I just gotta go watch this.
That's insane.
So, Henry, Emilia and I still had
some unanswered questions like,
why is the Northern Hemisphere
getting more total eclipses
than the southern hemisphere?
Why does the sun suddenly turn white
only during pure totality?
And how come
we still haven't figured
out what causes
these elusive shadow bands
on the ground?
Oh, that's so weird.
Okay, so we are on the
way to Burgos, Spain,
because it's going to be right
in the center of the moon's shadow.
So perfect for totality.
And we're also meeting up with NASA
and a bunch of other science groups
because they're launching a couple
of balloons up to the edge of space.
So they will actually be
filming the eclipse,
and hopefully they can
answer some of our questions.
Vamos!
Oh my God!
It's getting occluded, oh no!
Angela?
- Yes.
Oh, lovely to meet you.
I’m Emilia.
Oh, so nice to meet you.
This is Gregor.
Nice to meet you,
thanks for having us.
So, can I ask you?
Yeah.
Are those total
solar eclipses on your toes?
Yes. Totally geeking it up.
Yeah,
I guess, first question right off the bat.
How many eclipses have you seen?
So this will be
my fourth eclipse
and the third
total eclipse.
There's lots of folks here
who have seen many more than me.
Eight or even as many as 12. That's crazy.
So how rare is it
that Spain is getting two
total solar eclipses in
less than 12 months?
If you picked any random point
on any place on the earth,
it's about every 300 years
that the eclipse will repeat there.
But then there are some places, you know,
where there happens to be occurrences,
because there is kind of a pattern
to the eclipses.
You can see one of those patterns if you map out the paths of all total solar eclipses
between 2000 BCE and 3000 CE.
Notice that the Northern Hemisphere
consistently gets more eclipses,
about 15% more than the
Southern Hemisphere.
Now for there to be a
total solar eclipse
where the moon completely
covers the sun,
you want it to be
bigger than the sun in the sky.
Now, the biggest factor for
that is the moon's elliptical orbit.
Sometimes it's further from the Earth,
sometimes closer.
So over the course of the month,
its apparent area increases by up to 30%.
But the Earth's orbit around
the sun is also elliptical.
So from our point of view,
the sun's area is about 7% smaller in
July than it is in January.
Which means there is a higher chance
of a total solar eclipse around July.
But that's also when it's mostly
the north half of Earth
that is tilted towards the sun,
the Northern Hemisphere summer.
So that's where the total eclipses
tend to fall.
Now the Southern Hemisphere
is actually going to get
more annular eclipses
where the moon is slightly
smaller than the sun
so you have this ring of sunlight
around it.
And that's because during the southern
summer the sun is actually closer.
All of this is actually going to flip,
because the Earth precesses around
its axis and its elliptical orbit
also slowly shifts around the sun.
In about 9500 years,
it will be the Southern Hemisphere
that gets more total solar eclipses.
Now, there is another interesting pattern
that shows up when you look at all
types of solar eclipses,
including annular and partial ones too.
So I crunched some numbers,
like 5000 years of eclipses.
And if you look at how many happened
per year, there's never a year
without some sort of solar eclipse,
which kind of feels mind boggling.
You at least have to get two
and sometimes you can get five.
How do you get five?
- Yeah, yeah I know.
Check this out, so:
The moon's orbit is tilted about
five degrees out of the Earth sun plane.
So most times the moon passes
in front of the sun
It's at the wrong height
to cast a shadow on Earth.
And that's why we don't get
a solar eclipse every month.
But there are these two nodes
along the moon's orbit where it does
actually cross the Earth-Sun plane.
And throughout the year,
both of these nodes are going to land
nicely in between the Earth and the Sun.
This happens about six months apart,
and it opens a window
of around 34 days
where solar eclipses become possible.
And these are called eclipse seasons.
This is huge window to get eclipses.
- Yeah.
So as long as you get a new moon
somewhere inside of this eclipse window,
you get an eclipse.
But it turns out
you have to get at least one.
The reason is
the eclipse season is 34 days,
but a new moon happens every 29.5 days.
Of course.
So you can't go through an eclipse season
without the new moon happening
at least once.
However you roll the dice,
it always has to land
inside the eclipse season at least once.
So you always get two a year.
Great.
Yeah, right?
Now, if the new moon falls
towards the middle of an eclipse season,
it usually produces
a total or an annular eclipse,
and you can only fit one of those types
of eclipses into a season.
So you can get about two per year.
Yeah, this doesn't seem rare,
definitely not once in a lifetime.
Yeah, but it gets worse
because if you also count
partial eclipses,
those happen more towards the edges.
And because they happen to the edges.
You can get two
in a single eclipse season.
Or you can get four a year.
But wait, then how do you get five?
Yeah. The thing is,
the eclipse seasons themselves
also drift around the Earth's orbit.
So if you start on January 1st
and you get an eclipse
really, really soon into the year,
you can hit like a partial
and then another partial.
And then as you're moving,
these eclipse seasons are shifting.
So you get another one and another one
and then you think you're done.
But the eclipse season has actually
already shifted into December.
And then you get a final one.
So you can get up to five.
Woah.
Okay, wait, I realized
I forgot to tell you
my favorite fact out of this, out
of this whole discussion, and that's that
if you look at the eclipse season,
when the eclipse happens,
the solar eclipse here,
and you rewind by about two weeks,
you'll realize that now the Earth is in
between the sun and the moon.
So you get a lunar eclipse.
So you get a lunar eclipse, which means
every time there is a solar eclipse,
it is accompanied by a lunar eclipse
either two weeks before or after.
Oh, that's so cool. Yeah.
So there's one happening in two weeks.
Oh, amazing. Yeah, yeah, it's really cool.
I actually tried
to find an answer to this question,
but if you look at timelapses
taken during the eclipse.
You'll see that the partial parts
are usually like yellowish in color.
And then the totality is white.
If you Google on Google you get like a little animation and it turns white.
Yellow, and then it's white
and then it's yellow again.
I could not find a satisfying scientific
explanation for why that happens.
It's so bright, right?
In order to take those timelapse pictures,
you have to put a filter in front of it.
And so the most common with those filters,
it's that kind of reddish orange color.
So it's just the most common
filter makes it that color
because the sun is white.
But then it's dim enough that we can look
right at it during totality.
And so you see white.
- Yeah
It's just a filter, okay.
It's just the filter.
Maybe I can show you where we're at. Sure.
You can kind of get set up. Hey.
We're a NASA funded lab in Bozeman, Montana,
and this is an extension of what's called
the
Nationwide Eclipse Ballooning Project.
So we studied the 2023 and 2024 eclipse.
So we have two teams
in Reykjavik, Iceland, and we have three
teams here in Spain.
The Iceland teams are launching
essentially weather balloons, radiosondes.
And then we're launching what we call
larger engineering balloons here.
Look, cowboy engineering here.
What are you doing?
We attach this to our basically
the balloon.
Like right below where we're connecting
the balloon to the payload.
And usually we have a little bit
more sophisticated weights,
but we didn't want to just ship
weights to Spain with us.
So we took water bottles
and filled them with rocks.
I love it, I love it.
We have a little bag of like, souvenir
kind of things, like signed NASA stickers
and things like that
that we're going
to send up on the balloon.
This is going up so you can sign it.
- Hey!
You're signing it ‘Eclipse’?
I mean, Eclipse 2026,
I want to show it off
I thought you were going to say
like ‘Henry’ or something.
So, “Henry was here”?
We're not putting you
in the balloon, though, so...
We're gonna set up kind of in the middle
just because of the wind direction
at the moment.
Okay.
So right now the wind's going
the wrong way from the forecast.
Right. Blowing it that way.
It’s just finding a way to be far enough
that we don't hit the church.
How strong does the wind
have to be for you to hit the church?
Like it's pretty far away, no?
It is. We just have to outclimb it
before we get there.
Okay.
It's kind of weird.
I feel like
it was one of those things
where I'd seen pictures of them,
but I didn't realize how much it
just looked like a regular balloon,
but just super sized.
On the count of three,
one, two, three.
Amazing.
That launch went absolutely perfectly,
and right now our cameras are on their way
up to the edge of space.
But about 3000km away
NASA's launching
another eclipse mission, one mounted
on a 70 year old Cold War
era bomber plane.
They're trying to chase the totality
for as long as they can,
but surprisingly,
this is actually already been attempted.
In 1973, the Concorde went Mach 2
and stayed in the totality for 74 minutes.
Here on the ground, the longest
anyone's going to be able to see
the totality is two minutes
and 18 seconds.
And with NASA's jet going at 460mph,
they're going to be able
to stay in the totality for
just around three minutes.
It doesn't seem worth it,
but they're not just trying to stay in it longer.
Compared to a balloon,
which is a bit shaky.
A jet is much more stable, so it lets them
mount much more sensitive equipment
so they can study
a very specific part of the sun,
part of the sun, that once led to the
discovery of a fake element.
On the total eclipse of
the 18th of August, 1868,
French astronomer
Jules Janssen went to India
to look at a part of the sun
that's normally outshone from observation,
the prominences.
Arcs of glowing gas at the very edge.
He put a slit in front of a prism
and broke their light into its constituent wavelengths.
Out came five bright bands.
One of them matched no element
known on Earth.
Two months later, the English astronomer
Norman Lockyer saw the same line.
He called it helium, after Helios,
the Greek god of the sun.
The next year, other scientists
used the same method on the hotter corona
and found another unexplained band.
For 70 years it was thought to be
an element called coronium,
but in 1939 it turned out to be iron,
so hot that 13 of its electrons
had been ripped away.
So an eclipse led to discovering
both a real element and a fake one.
Now, to study the eclipse, Janssen used a slit,
but you actually don't have to.
So here I've cut out a triangle shape
in this cardboard,
and we're going to see the shadow
that it casts.
You can see there's
this projection of light
that makes a triangle, not too surprising,
but watch what happens as I slowly
move it away from the ground.
You'll see that triangle slowly morphs
into a circle.
I can even take this eclipse shape,
which looks like an eclipse
when it's close to the ground, but
I pull it again and it's always a circle.
Gregor, what are you seeing brother?
Wait, let me switch the glasses.
Oh, we're getting, like,
a nice croissant shape.
You know, I think it's called a crescent.
No no no no no no no.
A croissant, it's like very thick.
You check it out. Check it.
Yeah. No.
It's cool.
Here we take those same cardboard
cutouts
Here's the one with the triangle.
And again, you're seeing a triangle.
But look what happens when I move it away.
Look, it's a crescent.
How cool is that? Okay, and
I can do it with another shape.
I'm gonna try with this star shape,
which again, close up.
But if I move away? This star...
Also a crescent.
How sick is that?
You can even do it.
With something like this,
with all these little circular holes.
Circle. That's a circle. But even quicker.
A bunch of
little crescents.
That's amazing. Right? Come on, come on.
See, when the cardboard is high enough,
you're no longer looking at the hole,
but a projection of the light source
itself.
Light travels in straight lines,
so a ray leaving the top of the sun has to
angle downward to get through the hole.
So it lands at the bottom here.
The top goes to the bottom
and the left flips to the right.
Everything crosses at the hole and
it comes out on the other side reversed,
which means that during an eclipse,
the crescents on the ground
point the opposite
way to the crescents in the sky.
All cameras actually work like this,
flipping your image.
But to get this effect,
you need the point to be rather small,
it's like a pinhole camera.
That's why all the spaces between leaves
and a tree are perfect.
During an eclipse,
they all become crescents.
And there's another crazy effect.
Watch my hand.
The shadows around my fingers
are quite fuzzy, but if I turn my hand
90 degrees, those same shadows
suddenly become much sharper.
As we approach totality,
every object has a sharp direction
and a soft one, 90 degrees apart.
Take one point source of light, on its own
it casts a perfectly sharp shadow,
but add a second point, also perfectly
sharp, but arriving at a different angle.
Now, where the two shadows overlap,
you get full darkness,
but out at the edges,
where only one of them lands,
you get half the light.
If you do it for more and more points,
well, those edges
start to stack up into a gradient,
and that's what makes the blur.
And during an eclipse, you're left with
this sliver shape. In the tall direction,
it stays roughly the same width as normal.
That's why in this direction
you still get blurry shadows.
But change your orientation 90 degrees
and now, it's much more narrow.
So now it's like a point source again.
That's why the shadows in this direction
are perfectly sharp.
So we're a few minutes from totality.
And, what we're going to do
is we're going to hold up this sheet,
and what we're looking for
are these long moving shadows.
They're sometimes called snake shadows
because of how they move.
So you're talking about seconds
before totality
that you'll see these shadow bands occur
so maybe 20s, 10s before totality.
And so you really have to be, you know,
looking for them and aware
that they're going to exist.
Gosh, I'm a bit stressed about us
filming these now.
- Oh,
you'll be fine.
Like they're
either going to be pronounced,
you're going to be able to capture them,
or they're going to be so subtle
that nobody's going to see them anyway.
Is that it?
No, no, I think there is a little
something, like it's faint.
Oh, that's so weird.
See? Did you see it? Like it's
definitely there.
I don't know, I felt like
you were just moving the sheet.
No. Come on.
It was there, like, they are real.
We saw it, we saw it.
It was faint.
There is still some mystery
around shadow bands,
but exactly what causes them,
there is still some discovery there.
And so, it's absolutely an open question.
Right as you get to the final seconds of light,
before the eclipse
and you just get it's a Bailey's beads,
where you just get a single point of light,
or just a few points of light
along the limb.
The leading theory
is that these narrow beams of light
pass through many layers of air,
of varying temperature and densities.
Each of the boundaries
between those layers of air
refract the light, bending it
this way and that.
This is actually the same effect
that makes starlight twinkle.
But if that were the whole story,
as you went up through the atmosphere,
surely you wouldn't
see these shadow bands.
Did you hear?
Because there was an experiment
done in Burgos by an army engineer
in 1905 in the 1905 eclipse,
going up in a hydrogen balloon?
Oh, wow.
And he was actually looking for shadow
bands.
Oh, really?
So they launched these balloons.
They've put these big white sheets
under the balloons, to try and spot it,
And then they weren't
seeing anything, there standing at it,
and then all of a sudden,
someone pointed out
they were just everywhere, like,
on their hands, on the basket.
And they saw them everywhere,
but not on the white sheet.
They just they were just surrounded by it.
But again, someone was already testing it,
trying to test it,
at altitude back in 1905, right here.
That's amazing.
But what's going on there?
Is there another explanation?
So there are, the other thing
that is coming into effect
there, was the actual
topology of the moon itself.
So those different point sources, as they
line up and interfere with each other,
that's where you get
some of those sort of secondary effects
and make them more pronounced,
because you have
you can imagine it like in a theater.
If you could picture yourself in a theater
and you have one spotlight shining,
you have one point source.
If you had three spotlights,
you're going to get some interesting
sort of overlapping shadows,
and that's one of those effects that
amplify that, the shadow bands.
Oh that's cool.
15 seconds.
Okay, quick whip the glasses on.
Oh my gosh.
Wow. That's so strange.
Man. This is, this is so crazy.
Unbelievable.
I don't know what I was
imagining,
but this is so much more insane.
Everyone is going wild.
I love this guy.
Oh my God, you can see
the corona. And look at that, like,
really bright spot on the left.
Like sticking out. It's like ethereal.
Is that like a solar flare?
I don't, I don't know
I don't know what the words are.
I'm just like, this is cool.
Yeah, right,
- Its the 360!
- Oh, the 360 yeah, you're right.
There's a 360 sunset.
Oh my goodness!.
- I love that you're have a good time here, right.
It's incred... I know you?
Where are you from?
- Veritasium is the channel.
Jesus Christ, this guy's from Veritasium.
This is amazing.
It’s coming back, it’s coming back!
Look at the sky. It's unbelievable.
It's made my... my life.
It's got me unreasonably fired up
and then like, whoa!
And then that ring in the sky.
This is sweet.
Whoooaa, I have never been this
pumped up
on a natural event before, my god.
Bro how was that?
How do you feel, man?
It was insane.
Really, I don't know,
I just can't explain it.
Looking at it in person,
it is kind of cataclysmic.
You gotta cry.
We're up at the crack of dawn.
Chasing this balloon.
It did this crazy path, and then ended up
falling much closer than they thought.
Still probably going to be in some farmers
field somewhere.
Might have to do a little hike to get it.
Do we go for it? I mean, I don't know.
He's going for it.
And then
we have our cameras, so that's good.
So this is the one. Yeah.
Okay.
Cool.
Something going on.
That's crazy.
That's so cool.
Favorite shots of the shadow
are where you can just see part of it,
like receding.
Yeah.
So, we had about a seven hour drive
to get here, so we had plenty of time
to catch up on podcasts.
And we ended up listening to one
from today's sponsor, 80,000 hours.
It was about the Fermi Paradox
and some potential solutions.
It was pretty intriguing.
If you're into long conversations
that dig into big ideas,
their podcast is worth checking out.
80,000 hours is a nonprofit
that's built around a simple idea.
Your career is about 80,000 hours long.
That's a huge chunk of your life,
and it's probably your best shot
at making a real impact on the world.
What I like is they don't just tell you
to follow your passion.
Their advice is actually evidence based.
It's supported by over
a decade of research.
The site's got career guides, deep dives
into different paths, and a job board
that's full of high impact roles
and all of it,
the podcast, the research, the guides.
It's all completely free
because they're a nonprofit.
They're not trying to sell you anything.
So if you're trying to figure out
your next step or just curious
how to have more impact with your work,
head to 80000hours.org/Veritasium.
It'll get you their
free career guide, which walks you through
what makes for a high impact career,
it might give you some ideas
you might not have considered,
and it'll help you
turn them into an actual plan.
It'll also sign you up for their newsletter,
so you'll get updates on new research
and job opportunities
a couple times a month.
Thanks to 80,000 hours
for sponsoring this one and as always,
thanks to you for watching.
One last thing.
I wanted
to thank Astrum, and if you want to learn
more about The Sun's corona,
you can check out their video
in the description.
Also, thank you to Exploratorium for
letting us link into their live stream.
And of course, these guys, the team
from NASA borealis for all of their help.
Yeahhhh.
So we've taken a bunch of stickers
and we flew them to the edge of space.
You can see them right
here. We're now all signing them.
It went to what, 92,000ft?
Yeah like 30km? Insane.
If you guys want your hands on one,
we're going to give them out
to our Patreon members. It's totally free.
So if you want to check that out,
the link is also in the description.